A Guide to the Leander James McCormick Collection of Papers and Scale Models concerning the Inventions of Robert McCormick of Rockbridge County, Virginia, 1878-1910
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Leander James McCormick Collection of Papers and Scale Models concerning the Inventions of Robert McCormick of Rockbridge County, Virginia 1878-1910
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
7027
This collection consists of 23 manuscript letters and affadavits and 8 scale models.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
According to the 1910 Sept. 12 affadavit of James Hall Shields, the models were constructed prior to 1894 by Leaner [James] McCormick, son of Robert McCormick. The models, and the manuscripts collected by Leander, were inherited by his son, Robert Hall McCormick II, and then in turn by his son, Robert Hall McCormick II, and then in turn by his son, Robert Hall McCormick III of Chicago, Illinois.
Alternate Form Available
The collection, augmented with six copies of The Life and Works..., was presented for the Library of the University of Virginia by Robert Hall McCormick III on April 8, 1960 and formally accessioned by the Manuscripts Department on March 11, 1963. A display case for the permanent exhibition of the models was presented by the estate of Leander J. McCormick. An additional copy of The Life and Works....(bound in brown covers vice the blue covers of the previous six) was received from the Gifts and Exchange Department of the University of Virginia Library on February 17, 1971. On February 21, 1971, the manuscripts were removed from the binder in which they were presented and individually filed in acid-free folders.
Scope and Content Information
The Leander James McCormick Collection of Papers and Scale Models concerning the Inventions of Robert McCormick consists of 23 manuscript letters and affadavits, 1878-1910, in testimony of the invention of the reaper by Robert McCormick [1780-1846], 7 copies of The Life and Works of Robert McCormick Including his Invention of the Reaper, and 8 scale models of Robert McCormick's inventions.
Contents List
- Letters and Affidavits
  Most are published in The Life and Works of Robert McCormick, below [some incorrect dates]. Most are endorsed by Leander J. McCormick.
  - Affidavit of Horatio Thompson 1878 Sept. 9, 3 p
  - Affidavit of Zacariah J. McChesney 1878 Sept. 9, 3 p
  - Affidavit of Thomas S. Preston 1878 Sept. 10, 4 p
  - William S. McCormick to Leander J. McCormick 1878 Nov. 7, 2 p
  - William S. McCormick to Leander J. McCormick 1878 Nov. 7, 2 p
  - Affidavit of Robert McCormick 1879 Feb. 18, 2 p
  - Affidavit of William S. McCormick 1880 June 5, 3 p
  - Affidavit of Joseph Anderson 1881 March 16, 4 p
  - John H. B. Shultz to Leander J. McCormick 1894 Sept. 26, 1 p
  - Henry Shultz to Leander J. McCormick 1894 Sept. 27, 2 p. w/env.
  - Thomas H. McGuffin, A. Horace Henry to Leander J. McCormick 1894 Oct. 26, 2 p. w/env.
  - John H. Rush to Leander J. McCormick 1894 Nov. 20, 1 p.
  - William Steele to Leander J. McCormick 1895 Jan. 22, 1 p. w/env.
  - John H. B. Shultz to Leander J. McCormick 1897 Nov. 15, 2 p
  - Affidavit of Henrietta Maria McCormick 1898 Aug., 2 p
  - Serena McC. Hogshead to Leander J. McCormick 1899 March 7, 1 p
  - Lucy Steele to Leander J. McCormick 1899 March 15, 2 p
  - James E. A. Gibbs to Leander J. McCormick 1899 May 20, 1 p
  - James E. A. Gibbs to Leander J. McCormick 1899 May 31, 2 p. w/env.
  - James E. A. Gibbs to Leander J. McCormick 1899 May 31, 1 p. w/env.
  - Affidavit of Leander J. McCormick 1899 June 28, 1 p
  - C[harles] R. McCormick, Ellen McC. Raney to R. Hall McCormick 1910 June 16, 2 p
  - Affidavit of James Hall Shields 1910 Sept. 12, 8 p
  - envelopes n.d., 4 items
  - Copies of articles relating to the gift of the Leander J. McCormick Observatory to the University of Virginia ca. 1885
- Published Works
  - The Life and Works of Robert McCormick Including his Invention of the Reaper by R. Hall McCormick and James Hall Shields (n.p.) 1910, 50 p. & 9 plates ea. 31X21cm.
    6 copies with untrimmed blue paper covers
    1 copy with brown paper covers
- Scale Models
  The models, constructed by Robert McCormick's son, are on permanent display in the University of Virginia Library.
  - Double-acting bellows
  - Hydraulic engine
  - Original reaper invented and constructed in 1831
  - "The Old Reliable." Reaper of Robert McCormick, improved and perfected with raker's stand added by his son, Leander J. McCormick
  - Reciprocating and revolving horsepower for operating hempbrake, feed cutter and other machinery
  - Revolving horsepower with cogwheel attachment to prevent slippage operating grist mill, with feed cutter
  - Hempbrake
  - Improved hempbrake with revolving feed apron